Oh, how much further?
噢, 还有多远？
There's no sign of the toy soldiers now.
没有那些玩具士兵的踪迹了
- We've got to get out of this place.
- Look.
- 我们必须离开这个地方  - 快看
There's a house.
那里有栋房子
Creag an tuire!
Jamie!
Jamie!﻿
- Doctor!  - It's all right, Zoe.
- 博士!  - 没事的, Zoe
Well, come on. If you want to play games,
let's get on with it.
好了, 来吧．如果你们想要玩有些, 我们就来玩玩
(ECHOING LAUGHTER)
What's that?
那是什么？
I have to make up his face again.
我必须重新拼他的脸
- You did this before!  - Yes.
- 之前是你干的！  - 是的
That's how Jamie's face got changed.
这就是 Jamie 的脸为什么变样了
- You got it all wrong!
- What? No, no.
- 因为你完全搞错了！  - 什么？不, 不是
Well, I was rushed.
只是, 我太匆忙了
Now, then... There we are.
现在, 这样... 好了
All right, I know!
都对了, 我就知道！
There we are.
好啦
One... Now, then... Yes, that's his nose.
You can't mistake his nose, can you?
一个...现在是...对了, 这是他的鼻子．你不会搞错吧？
And...
还有...
(LAUGHS)
There you are, you see!
给你贴上, 你看！
Jamie! Thank goodness you're back.
Jamie! 感谢老天你回来了
- I haven't been anywhere.
- You've got your face back.
- 我哪儿也没去啊  - 你的脸弄回来了
- I have?  - Yes. Look.
- 有吗？  - 是的, 你看
You're right, I have! That's much better.
你说对了, 的确！这好多了
- Ah! The house.
- Yes. Come along. Let's go inside.
- 啊! 那个房子  - 是的, 都过来, 我们进去
(CREAKING DOOR)
(ECHOING GLUGGING, DRIPPING SOUNDS)
Well, there must be somebody here.
This... These candles are alight. Ugh!
喏, 这里肯定有个人．这个...这些蜡烛都亮着呢．哈！
- Hello there!
- (VOICE ECHOES)
你好啊！
One, two, three, four tunnels leading off.
一, 二, 三, 四条隧道在前面
- We could easily get lost in there.
- Just a moment.
- 我们很容易在里面迷路的  - 等一下
What's he found?
他找到了什么？
A ball of twine.
一个线团
Hmm... Oh, yes...
This must have been an invitation.
嗯...噢, 是的...这肯定是一个邀请
Why?
为什么？
It's the classical way of getting through a maze.
Tie that to the door, will you?
这是穿越迷宫的经典方法．把这个栓在门上, 好吗？
It's locked.
锁住了
- Then we ARE meant to go on.
- Yes, I think we are.
- 那我们就更应该继续了  - 是的, 我觉得是
But that means that wherever we go,
at any time, they know.
但这也意味着,不管我们去哪里, 不管何时, 他们都知道
They're expecting us.
他们在等着我们
Yes... Don't break the thread. Come along.
是的...别把线弄断了．都来吧
- Which way, do you think?   - To the right.
- 那条路, 你觉得？  - 右边
(DOCTOR) They both look equally
unattractive to me.
这两条路对我没有什么吸引力
It must be to the right.
I've been working it out.
肯定是右边．我已经基本搞明白了
- Doctor...  - Shh! How?
- 博士  - 嘘！怎么?
As soon as we avoided the dead ends,
it soon fell into a clear pattern.
一旦我们排除走不通的路，规律很快就出来了
One left, two right, three left, four right
and so on. A simple arithmetical progression.
左一右二, 左三右四, 以此类推．非常简单的数学序列
- Yes. But Doctor...  - Shh!
- 是的，但是博士...  - 嘘!
What it is to have an arithmetical brain!
What do you want?
什么东西有一个懂数学的大脑？你想要什么?
The thread's run out. Should we not go back?
线团到头了．我们不往回走吗？
No. You stay here
and Zoe and I will explore a little further.
不, 你待在这里．Zoe 和我往前探探
There must be another way out of this maze.
I need to find it.
肯定有另外一条路走出迷宫, 我得找到它
They don't want us to find a way out,
only a way in!
他们不想让我们找到出去的路, 只有进来的路！
(GLUGGING, DRIPPING)
I was right. This isn't the way out.
我说对了, 这不是出去的路
We're in the middle of the maze.
我们在迷宫的中央
- Doctor, I don't like it. Let's go.
- Just a moment.
- 博士, 我不喜欢这个, 我们走吧  - 等一下
I was rather expecting a welcoming
committee, but perhaps I was wrong.
我本来还相当期待有个欢迎派对, 看来也许我想错了
I hope you were!
我期望你想错了！
There WAS someone here, not so long ago either. Look!
的确有人在这里, 就在不久之前．看！
(BOTH) Oh!
噢！
There's some tracks of an animal too.
这里还有动物的痕迹
- Oh, Doctor, let's go...
- (FEROCIOUS ROAR)
噢，博士，我们走吧
- It couldn't be!
- What?
- 这不可能！  - 什么？
I know it's silly, but do you remember
the story of the Minotaur?
我知道有点蠢, 但你还记得牛头怪的故事吗？
Half-man, half-bull, yes.
半人半牛, 记得
And he lived in the heart of a labyrinth.
而他就住在一个迷宫的中央
And there were human sacrifices!
还拿活人献祭！
Exactly, but I don't think
we need be too alarmed...
真的是, 但我不觉得我们需要太恐慌...
(FEROCIOUS ROAR)
As long as we're quite certain
that the Minotaur is only a...
毕竟我们非常确定牛头怪只是一个....
Doctor, look!
博士, 快看！
(ECHOING, SNARLING ROAR)
Zoe, It's a legend.
只是一个传说．Zoe
- But it's there!  - No!
- 但它就在那儿！  - 不是！
The Minotaur is a mythical beast. Say it!
＂牛头怪只是神话里的＂, 快念！
The Minotaur is a mythical beast.
It doesn't exist!
牛头怪只是神话里的, 它并不存在!
(ROARING STOPS)
It's gone!
它消失了!
Yes.
是的
I'm afraid we made it
too difficult for it to stay.
估计是我们让它无法待在这里
Come on. Let's go and find Jamie.
快点, 我们去找 Jamie
So that's how you can see, is it?
所以这就是为什么你能看到我们, 对不？
With that wee lighthouse of yours.
就用你这个小小的灯塔
(MASTER) No! Brainless idiot.
不！无脑的蠢人！
Get yourself free. Don't let the boy escape!
把那东西弄开，别让那小伙子跑了！
I think this is the place.
我觉得就是这个地方了
Yes. There's no sign of him.
是的。但没他的影子
I'm sure he wouldn't have gone off without...
我确信他不会走掉...
- What's that?  - His jacket.
- 这是什么？  - 他的外套
- Well, he must be around here somewhere.
- Jamie!
- 那, 他肯定在这附近某个地方  - Jamie!
Who's that?
谁在那里？
- My dear sir!  - Your servant, sir.
- 亲爱的先生  - 为你服务, 先生
- You have a knack of turning up unexpectedly.
- Have you seen Jamie?
- 你突然就冒出来了  - 你看到 Jamie 了吗？
I walked alone
but saw no sign of any inhabitants.
我一个人过来的, 没有见到过其他人的影子
- (ZOE) Are you absolutely positive?
- I would not impose any falsities upon you.
- 你完全确定吗？  - 我不会对你提供任何虚假信息
- I adhere strictly to truth.
- Of course.
- 我严格遵循真相  - 当然是
This person who controls this place...
控制这个地方的的这个人...
- The Master?
- The Master? Yes?
- 大师？  - 大师？怎么？
Have you seen him?
你见过他？
Upon occasion he has been pleased
to grant me an audience.
偶尔他会跟高兴给我当一个听众
Where might I find him?
我能在哪里找到他？
The Master's palace is no ordinary edifice,
but a citadel,
大师的宫殿不是普通的地方，而是一座城堡
a walled town at the top of a hill or cliff,
the highest in the kingdom.
在山顶上用墙围了起来，那是这个王国最高的地方
Now I think I understand.
现在我觉得我明白了
May I ask, sir, where you come from?
Would it not be Nottingham?
我能问问, 先生, 你从那里来？不会是诺丁汉吧？
My father had a small estate in Nottingham.
I was the third of five sons.
我父亲在诺丁汉有一个小庄园, 他有五个儿子, 我是老三
He sent me to Emmanuel College
in Cambridge at 14 years old,
我14岁的时候, 他送我去剑桥的伊曼纽尔学院
where I applied myself close to my studies,
learning navigation and other parts mathematics...
我在那里刻苦学习，学习航海和和数学的其它方面...
(BOTH) Useful for those who intend to travel,
这些对于打算出去旅行的人都是很有用的
as I always believed
it would be my fortune to do.
我一直都相信, 旅行才是我的命运
Now I know who you are, sir.
现在我知道你是谁了, 先生
- Your name is Lemuel Gulliver!
- Your servant, sir.
- 你的名字是雷米尔-格列弗!  - 愿为你服务, 先生
- Gulliver?  - Yes.
- 格列弗?   - 是的
Oh, no!
噢, 不会吧！
I'd need to be a human fly to get up that lot.
我得有双翅膀才能到那里去
I can't go back, though.
What I really need is a...
但我又不能后退．我现在真正需要的就是...
Who says wishes don't come true?
谁说愿望不会成真？
Ouch!
嗷!
I suppose you know that hurts?
我觉得你应该知道这很疼吧？
- You mean this is your hair?  - Of course
- 你是说这是你的头发？ - 当然
I don't object to people climbing it -
I'm quite used to it, actually -
我倒是不反对有人顺着它爬上来 - 事实上我都习惯了
- but you would keep tugging so.
- I'm sorry.
- 但你却一直这么拽着  - 对不起
- Are you a prince?  - No. Why?
- 你是一位王子吗？  - 不是, 怎么了？
You're supposed to be.
I'm a princess, but I suppose you knew that.
你应该是．我是一位公主, 我觉得你知道这个
(见童话故事《长发公主》)
My name's Rapunzel. You're not
a woodcutter's son, by any chance?
我的名字是 Rapunzel．你不会碰巧是伐木工人的儿子吧？
- No. I'm the son of a piper.
- How very disappointing.
- 不是, 我是风笛手的儿子  - 真让人失望
In that case, I think you'd better go. Goodbye.
这样的话，我想你最好离开．再见
- Your Highness, wait!  - Well?
- 公主殿下，等等!  - 怎么？
I can't go back there. It's a sheer drop.
And I can't just stand out here.
我没法回那条路, 太陡峭了。我也不能就这样站在这外面
I'll have to climb in through the window.
我必须从窗户爬进去
- I don't know if that would be allowed.
- I won't stay long.
- 我不知道这是否允许  - 我不待太久
Just passing through, you might say.
只是穿过，可以说
- Och, please.
- It's a great pity you're not a prince.
- 噢, 求你了  - 你不是一位王子真是太可惜了
You'd have made rather a good one.
你本可以当一个好王子的
Well, I suppose you'd better come inside.
这样, 我觉得你最好进来
For goodness' sake, be quiet.
保险起见, 保持安静
Rapunzel!
Rapunzel!﻿
Your Highness, where have you gone?
殿下, 你去哪儿了？
Don't be silly. I'm not going...
别傻了, 我可不会...
Hey, this doesn't look like
the inside of a princess's castle to me.
嘿, 一个公主的城堡里面看起来不像是这个样子的啊
...but it would not be proper to trouble you
with the particulars of my adventures.
但拿我的历险过程中的细节来烦扰你们，不是太合适
I wouldn't dream of detaining you.
我并没有想要拖住你
Having been condemned, by Nature and Fortune
to a restless and active life,
命运注定了我将一生奔波不休
I must take my leave of you. Farewell.
我必须得离开你们了。再会
Farewell.
再会
Why does he talk
in such an extraordinary way?
为什么他要用这样奇怪的方式说话？
He can only speak the words
that Dean Swift gave him to say.
他只能使用 Dean Swift 写过的那些语句
(Dean Swift: 格列弗游记 的作者)
That's ridiculous. There never was a Gulliver.
这太荒谬了, 从来没有一个格列弗
- He's a fictional character.
- Of course he is.
- 他是一个虚构的人物  - 他当然是
This world that we've tumbled into
is a world of fiction -
我们闯入的这个世界是一个虚构世界
''The Doctor and Zoe,
"博士和Zoe
''unable to find their companion in the labyrinth,
"在迷宫里面找不到他们的同伴
''decided to return to the cave in search of him,
"决定返回洞里去寻找他
''where a new terror awaited them.''
"一个新的恐怖在等着他们＂
That wasn't there before, was it?
刚才并没有这个, 是吧?
A statue.
一个雕像
(HISSING)
(DOCTOR) Medusa!
美杜莎!
''The Doctor and Zoe...
were face to face with Medusa.
"博士和Zoe...与美杜莎面对面了
''One glance from her eyes would...
"只要被她看一眼, 就会...
''would turn them to stone.''
"就会把他们变成石头＂
- Now we know what we have to do, Zoe.
- Yes.
- 现在我们知道要做什么了, Zoe  - 是的
(HISSING)
She's moving. She's going to look at us!
她在动了, 她要看我们了
- We have to say Medusa does not exist.
- But she does!
- 我们必须念＂美杜莎并不存在＂  - 但她存在啊
Zoe, Medusa is a myth.
Zoe, 美杜莎是个神话
If you believe in her,
she can turn us both to stone.
如果你相信她, 她就能把我们变成石头